Resume

Shubham Gupta

Azure Administrator/Cloud Operation Engineer Email Addresses: shubhamgupta.mg@gmail.com

Contact No.: 8800709656







Objective: Intend to build career in cloud computing platform to be in charge with leading corporate of hi-tech environment with committed and dedicated attitude, which will help the organization and me to explore myself. willing to work as a key player in challenging and creative environment with high endeavor to solve the problem.

Summary: An extremely driven and highly skilled with around 5+ years of experience in cloud services configuration and troubleshooting. Working in IT/SW industry as part of cloud and other technical roles with good communication interpersonal skills.

Key Skills and Certifications

Key Skill	Experience	Activities in Key Skill	Certification
Microsoft	3.8+ Years	VM Creation & Config, Availability Set & Availability	AZ 900
Azure		Zones, Virtual Network, Resource Group, Load Balancer,	
		Application gateway, Traffic Manager, VNET Peering &	AZ 104
		Global VNEET Peering, RPO & RTO, Application Insight,	
		Diagnostic setting, Azure Site Recovery, Azure Data	AZ 305
		Migrations, Azure Backups, Azure Storage Encryption,	
		Azure Monitor, Log Analytic Workspace, Azure Storage	
		account Config, Azure AD, RBAC, SAS, Conditional	
		Access, JIT Access, Azure AD Connect, Storage Replication,	
		Concept Of Storage Account, Network Watcher Tools,	
		Azure Sentinel, Azure Storage Account Access Tiers,	
		Immutable Storage, Redis Cache, Azure SQL Managed	
		Instance, Azure SQL Server, Azure Cosmos DB, Azure SQL	
		Elastic Pool, Azure Data Lake Storage Concept, Data	
		Transfer From On Premises to Azure, Knowledge Of	
		DevOps and CICD, Infrastructure tool as Terraform, CICD	
		tool as Jenkins, SCM tool as GIT, Configuration	
		management tool as Ansible, Automation Through	
		Powershell commands	
Windows	1.2Years	Installation & Configuration, Active Directory, DNS, DHCP,	
Server		User Creation & Deletion, Assign Group, Assign Permission,	
		Health Checkup, Compliance Related Activities	

Professional Experience

Company – Jio Platform Limited

From: May 2022 to Till Date

Roles and Responsibilities

- Implementation of Azure landing zone- Define Strategy, Plan, Ready, Adopt, Govern, Manage. Creation New EA subscription for landing zones, Create User & Assign Global admin Owner role,
- Connectivity of Sites via VPN- Site To Site VPN, Point to Site VPN, Express Route, Connectivity with Virtual WAN.
- Connectivity b/w VNets- VNet Peering, Global VNet Peering, Transit Gateway.
- Schedule Automation- Update management, Configure Management
- Monitoring- Metrics, Activity Log, Action Group, Logs by Azure monitor.
- Infra security- Azure Defender, Azure Firewall, NSG, Azure Sentinel.
- **Disaster Recovery** Configuration of Azure Site Recovery
- **Troubleshoot** Connectivity of Azure SQL server and postgress SQL DB with private endpoints, troubleshooting with help of Network Watcher Tool.
- Remote login of Virtual Machines via RDP, SSH, Bastion.
- HA Options- Virtual Machine in Availability Set, Availability Zones, VMSS(Virtual Machine Scale set).
- Backups- Configure Azure Backup by Recovery Service Vault. Backup policies.
- Load Balancing Azure Load Balancer, Application Gateway, Azure Traffic Manager, Azure Front Door, Implement NAT Gateway
- **Deployment of Compute Resources-** Virtual Machines (Portal, Template & Terraform), App service- Azure function, Logic apps, Web services etc
- Azure Active Directory- Assign Azure Active Directory Roles, Assign Role-based access control (RBAC), Configure App in AD, Create Tenant, Dynamic groups, Conditional Access, Identity Protection, MFA, PIM, Create Custom roles and assign Custom roles.
- **AD Synchronization** Azure AD Connect (Password Hash Synchronization, Pass Through Authentication, Password Write Back).
- Storage Storage (Standard and Premium Storage account), Types of storage (Blob, Table, File, Queue), Managed Disk, Storage Replication (LRS/ZRS/GRS/RA-GRS), Storage Encryption, Configure SAS (Shared Access Signature), Providing access to storage account via private endpoint, Concept of service endpoint. Creating the Azure SFTP service for Blob storage account, Azure Storage Encryption, Azure SQL Database, Manage identity Access- User Identity access, Service Identity Access.

• **Automation** - Working on Automation with Powershell & CLI based on requirement. DevOps and CICD with Jenkins, ansible, GIT and Terraform.

Company - Cloudxchange.io

From: Jan 2022- May 2022

Roles and Responsibilities

- Worked as Cloud Operation Engineer with Implementation of Azure landing zone- Define Strategy, Plan, Ready, Adopt, Govern, Manage. Creation New EA subscription for landing zones, Create User & Assign Global Admin Owner role, Create VNets and Subnet as per Customer Requirement.
- Involved in configuring virtual machines, Virtual network Resource groups, Azure site Recovery, RPO & RTO, Application Insight, Log from Diagnostic setting, Azure Sentinel, Azure Site Recovery, Import Export tool, Azure Storage Encryption, Azure SQL Database.
- Remote login to Virtual Machines to troubleshoot, monitor and deploy applications.
- Managing day to day activity of the cloud environment, supporting development teams with their requirements.
- Working on Microsoft Azure (Public) Cloud to provide IaaS support to client.
- Configure the VMs in Availability Set to provide higher Availability for VMs.
- Configure Azure Backup by Recovery Service Vault.
- Create the Virtual Network & VNET Peering, Global VNET Peering.
- Configure Azure Load Balancer, Application Gateway, Azure Traffic Manager, Azure Front Door
- Managing Azure VM from automation service and scheduler service.
- Analyze resource utilization and consumption.
- Create and configure storage accounts.
- Automate deployment of Virtual Machines (VMs).
- Create connectivity between virtual networks.
- Manage Azure Active Directory (AD).
- Manage role-based access control (RBAC).
- Configure SAS (Shared Access Signature)
- Azure AD Connect Password Hash Synchronization, Pass Through Authentication, Password Write Back.
- Good Concepts of Storage (Standard and Premium Storage account), types of storage (Blob, Table, File, Queue), Managed Disk, Storage Replication (LRS/ZRS/GRS/RA-GRS) etc.
- Troubleshooting Connectivity B/w Virtual Networks.

COMPANY- WIPRO INFOTECH PVT.LTD.

From: June 2018 – Dec 2021

Position: Computer application trainee

Roles and Responsibilities:

- Worked as Cloud Administrator on Microsoft Azure, involved in configuring virtual machines, Virtual network Resource groups, Azure site Recovery, RPO & RTO, Application Insight, Log from Diagnostic setting, Azure Sentinel, Azure Site Recovery, Import Export tool, Azure Storage Encryption, Azure SQL Database.
- Remote login to Virtual Machines to troubleshoot, monitor and deploy applications.
- Managing day to day activity of the cloud environment, supporting development teams with their requirements.
- Working on Microsoft Azure (Public) Cloud to provide IaaS support to client.
- Configure the VMs in Availability Set to provide higher Availability for VMs.
- Configure Azure Backup By Recovery Service Vault.
- Create the Virtual Network & VNET Peering, Global VNET Peering.

- Managing Azure VM from automation service and scheduler service.
- Analyze resource utilization and consumption.
- Create and configure storage accounts.
- Automate deployment of Virtual Machines (VMs) through Azure Virtual Desktop services.
- Create connectivity between virtual networks.
- Manage Azure Active Directory (AD).
- Manage role-based access control (RBAC).
- Configure SAS (Shared Access Signature).
- Azure AD Connect Password Hash Synchronization, Pass Through Authentication, Password Write Back.
- Good Concepts of Storage (Standard and Premium Storage account), types of storage (Blob, Table, File, Queue), Managed Disk, Storage Replication (LRS/ZRS/GRS/RA-GRS) etc.
- Troubleshooting Connectivity B/w Virtual Networks
- Managing customer environment with AVD.

Academic Qualification:

Degree / Qualification	Name of the Institute / School	University / Board	Marks Scored	Year of Passing
Bachelor of Computer Application	H.R. Institute of Technology, Ghaziabad, U.P.	Chaudhary Charan Singh University, Meerut, U.P.	72%	July 2018
Higher Secondary Education	JKG School, Nandgram, Ghaziabad, U.P.	Central Board of Secondary Education	74%	March 2015
Secondary School Certificate	JKG School, Nandgram, Ghaziabad, U.P.	Central Board of Secondary Education	78%	May 2013

Personal Details:

Name : Shubham Gupta Date of Birth : 11 June 1997

Marital status : Single

Languages : English, Hindi

LinkedIn : https://linkedin.com/in/shubham-gupta1106

Place: Ghaziabad

Date: 23/05/2023 (Shubham Gupta)